The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at OCW.MIT.edu.
PROFESSOR: So I am
going to start this talk
by explaining the title.
So we'll start with
active learning.
What is active learning?
In my mind, it's this
pretty broad term.
It's a form of learning that
attempts to involve students
more directly in the
learning process.
And there are all
sorts of things
that fall under the
umbrella of active learning.
So things like having
students engage in group
work, in class-wide
discussions, in debates,
acting out certain concepts,
group problem solving
sessions, all of these things.
And so in all of
those activities,
students are engaged.
They're not passively
listening to a lecture,
they're actively participating.
And there is some evidence
that this style of learning
is good for a lot of things.
There is evidence to support
the effectiveness of student
engagement in exam
scores, failure rates, how
well students remember content,
student attitudes, study
habits.
And there's also evidence
that active learning
has a disproportionate benefit
for minorities, students
from disadvantaged
backgrounds, female students,
and male dominated fields.
So there's evidence that active
learning creates this more
inclusive environment.
So it's this wide, wide
variety of techniques reported
to have a lot of benefits.
So that's active learning.
Now, what is 6.033?
So 6.033 is computer
systems engineering.
It's a required class
for all computer science
majors, which means as a
result, at MIT it's quite large.
So like Dipa said, we
have about 400 students.
It runs once a year.
So every spring we
get 400 new students.
Most of them are
juniors and seniors.
And in some ways, 033
is a typical MIT class.
We have lectures twice a week.
We have recitations
twice a week.
But in most other ways, 033
is not a typical MIT class.
For one, it's a CIM class.
So it's a Communications
Intensive in the Major class.
That means that most
of our assignments
are based around writing
or oral presentations.
It's not a class where students
are implementing or building
a lot of things.
We focus heavily on
reading and on writing.
In particular, we have
tutorial sections each week,
dedicated to the
communication material,
taught by dedicated
communication staff.
The major assignment in
033 is a design project.
It takes most of the semester.
The students completed in
teams, usually teams of three.
And it's comprised of a
few written assignments
and oral presentations.
One of our big focuses for that
project is getting students
to recognize the trade-offs
they need to make when they're
designing a system,
and getting them
to defend those trade-offs.
So this is not
just a class about
how computer systems work,
but how we design them,
how we decide what
choices to make when
we're building those systems.
So the last thing that
makes 033 pretty unique,
and is what I'm largely
going to talk about here,
is that our recitation
sections are pretty intense.
They are taught by faculty,
senior research staff.
We have about 25
students per section.
So you are right to think
that, oh, my gosh, they have
like 18 sections per semester.
We do.
It's a lot.
Each recitation focuses
around a technical paper
that the students
have read beforehand.
And the goal for those
discussion sections,
those recitations, is for them
to be largely discussion based.
And in fact, that has
always been the goal of 033.
033 has been around for
almost 50 years at this point.
It's been around since
before I was born.
And the goal has always
been for these recitations
to be discussion based.
During the recitations,
we're talking about,
we talk about the system
that the paper describes--
does it work?
What were the trade-offs
that the authors made?
Do we like this system?
How would you
design this system?
All right, so that is 033.
Now, why put active
learning into 033?
And you might think that it's
just because, well, there's
evidence that active
learning can be a good idea,
so why not try it?
That's fair.
We were actually trying to
solve a pretty specific problem
in the class though.
So like I said,
ideally the recitations
are based heavily
around discussion.
And again, that has
always been the goal.
Because this is a class about
system design, not just about
how these systems work,
one way that we teach
that is by having the
students analyze and critique
existing systems
before they go out
and try to design their own.
And so, what are the
goals of the designers?
Does the system
meet those goals?
Are those goals important?
If you were redesigning the
system, how would you do it?
What would your goals be?
What trade-offs would
you have to make?
Things like that.
A large part of that
instruction happens
in the recitation, where we're
having these discussions.
And they go and
apply those skills
to their design projects.
So to get that to happen, it's
important that the students are
engaged in recitation,
that they're
reading the paper beforehand,
they're asking questions,
they're answering questions,
they're coming prepared,
things like that.
And for a long time, that
was not happening for us.
We had a lot of
trouble with this.
We found that students weren't
willing to volunteer answers.
When we'd ask them a question,
nobody would raise their hand.
We found that some of
them weren't even reading
the paper beforehand.
So they're just kind
of coming in confused.
As a result of all of
this, our instructors
would end up spending
the first 15, 20, 25
minutes of the recitation
lecturing about the paper,
because so many of the
students didn't come prepared.
And then that just made things
worse, as you can imagine.
Students know that they're
going to come into recitation,
that they're going
to get a lecture,
so why bother reading the paper,
if your instructor is just
going to explain it to you.
And so it was just kind
of making things worse.
We weren't getting to teach
the material that we really
needed to teach, because
we were spending time
rehashing these papers.
The students
weren't learning how
to read these papers,
how to analyze them,
how to critique them.
And honestly, it
wasn't much fun.
It wasn't all that much
fun to teach this way.
Occasionally, we could get a
discussion going in a class.
But we would then encounter
another problem, which
is pretty common, where
we'd have a discussion,
but it would be dominated
by two or three students
in the room, the same
two or three students.
And then other students
are tuning out,
or even becoming sort of
visibly uncomfortable,
not wanting to
volunteer these answers.
So that's where we were.
And we had this problem.
We really wanted the recitations
to be this really fun place,
where the students were
coming, and they're
wrestling with all
of these new ideas
and proposing these new things.
But we didn't have that.
We had this place where
students aren't coming prepared,
or if they're prepared, if we
can get a discussion going,
it's not the kind of
discussion we want.
It's sort of dominated
by one or two people.
So after some
thinking, I thought
active learning might
be a good approach
to solve both of these problems.
So, as I mentioned
earlier, there's
some evidence that
active learning
can be good for creating
an inclusive environment
in a classroom.
So for instance, one
common technique,
which I will talk
a bit about later,
is you pose a
question to the class,
but put everybody
in small groups,
have the students
discuss in small groups,
and then kind of bring the
classroom back together
for a wide discussion.
Students are in
their groups, they
get a chance to kind of vet
their ideas with their peers.
It's sort of hard if you're
in a group of two or three
to not participate.
You sort of have
to say something.
So they'll get to vet
their ideas with people,
they'll get some reassurance.
And in theory, they are then
more willing to bring that idea
back to the whole class.
That type of activity can also
give you a relatively easy way
to make sure one person doesn't
dominate the discussion,
by saying, OK, I split you
guys up into five groups,
and let's hear from
each group now.
Moreover, I thought if we
did a lot of active learning,
it might keep the students
engaged for longer.
It would help us
avoid lecturing.
set this precedent
that you come to recitation
having read the paper,
we're not going to
lecture for you.
So that's kind of
where we're starting.
That's the baseline
for this talk.
Now my goal for all of you
is that this talk is, I hope,
exceedingly practical.
I'm going to talk about
some specific ways
that I trained my
staff to do this,
the types of active
learning activities
we do, some lessons
we've learned,
how we've evaluated our success.
I hope you'll be able to
apply some of these ideas
to your own classes if you want.
I do want to start,
though, with a disclaimer.
This is really a case study of
how active learning has worked
in 033.
I'm not here to make claims
that active learning is
a solution to all of
your teaching problems.
I think it's very good.
It's probably not the
solution to everything.
Nor am I even--
I'm not even here to
really evangelize it
over any other particular
pedagogical schemes.
I think it works well in 033,
I think we've done some really
cool things.
I hope you're excited
to hear about them.
So active learning.
As you've probably
picked up at this point,
what I'm going to talk about,
we're infusing the recitations
in 033 with active learning.
And so that means
that really it is
my recitation instructors
who are on the ground doing
a lot of this.
And I will admit, when
we were starting out,
I sort of thought--
I had this amazing idea to do
active learning recitations.
And I was like, well, I am done.
I have solved the problem.
I just told my instructors
to implement it.
It was like, guys,
active learning.
It didn't work.
I was perplexed, because I
told my instructors correctly
that these types
of activities would
help increase participation.
My instructors were the ones
complaining about the lack
of participation.
And so I just thought come
on, what's the problem.
Well it turns out you cannot
tell your instructors to do
a thing that they've never
done before and just have them
magically do it.
In particular, you can't
tell your instructors
to fundamentally change
the way they teach
and magically have that happen.
I would say it's
difficult enough
for us to change
the way we teach,
much less to get other people
to change the way they teach.
So the first part of
my talk is changing
the way other people
teach in four easy steps.
So step one is get
everyone on board.
So this is the first thing
that I did, last year in 033.
I will keep saying last
semester, but last year.
I presented active learning
as our primary goal
for the entire semester.
So we did not wait until
the course got settled down
to start doing it.
In fact, our very
first staff meeting,
which happens before the
semester has even begun,
was about active learning.
We had everyone on
the staff there.
So me, all of my
recitation instructors,
all of my TAs, all of the
communication instructors.
This is about 30
some people here.
And we talked about
active learning.
We talked about why it's a good
idea, the evidence that it's
a good idea, evidence that
it is better than lecturing.
We talked about why running the
recitations in this way would
support the other learning
objectives in 033,
in particular the objective
of getting students to design
their own systems and
evaluate their own tradeoffs.
I explained to my
instructors that there would
be extensive support for this.
And that we'd be checking
in throughout the semester
to make sure this was
really working for them
and working for the students.
Now I did expect some pushback
on this in this meeting.
Partly, I am asking a
lot of my staff here.
And also, I am a
lecturer in charge
of a lot of faculty, who have
been here for a very long time.
So I was not quite
sure how this would go.
I do not know if my
staff knew about this.
I actually went so far in
preparing for this staff
meeting to not only write
out all of my objectives
and why active learning
was a good idea,
but to write my own rebuttal
to myself and then rebut that.
So I sort of had, OK, if
I didn't want to do this,
I'd be asking--
well, I don't think
active learning is
a good idea, I don't
think this is going to work.
And I had prepared answers
for all of these questions.
I looked at the notes for that
meeting to prepare for this.
And it really went
on for quite a while.
I did not actually get
that much pushback here,
because my staff is amazing.
But also, I talked to a few of
my instructors ahead of time
about this, people who
had been with the class
for a while, who I knew would
be maybe a little bit more game
for this idea.
I kind of got them
on board first.
I also appealed to
everyone's scientific nature,
explaining that this was
somewhat of a research
project, which was true.
I did want to know
would this work in 033.
I was heavily biased
towards the fact
that I thought it
was going to work.
But we had methods to evaluate
this throughout the semester.
And I told them if
this goes horribly,
we won't keep doing it.
I'm not going to
burden you with this.
And I enthusiastically
mandated that this is what we
were trained for this semester.
In previous semesters,
I had suggested
some of these ideas,
encouraged my staff to try it.
And that really wasn't enough.
And so on the one hand,
get everyone on board.
It was one staff meeting.
I will say, it was
really tempting
for me to not have that
staff meeting so soon.
033 is such a big class.
It has so many people involved.
It feels like we're
just scrambling
to get the logistics worked
out in the first week or two.
Even for us assigning
our students to sections
is this whole thing.
But doing this really set the
tone for the whole semester.
I was kind of surprised
at how helpful this was.
Everybody knew the active
learning was important.
Even the people who weren't
the recitation instructors,
all the TAs, all the
communications instructors,
they knew that it
wasn't optional.
It was their primary
goal of the semester.
Any other changes that
we made in the class
were largely going to be
in support of this goal.
So step one, get everybody
on board with your mission.
Step two is do a lot of
work, do a lot of planning.
So step one was our
first staff meeting.
Step two, what's happening
in our second staff meeting.
So one of the things
that we did is
we talked about a pretty
well-known list of something
like 278 different active
learning activities.
I knew it was a
lot to ask really
anyone to read through all 278
active learning activities.
And so I annotated this list.
And we kind of
discussed the highlights
in the staff meeting.
I am going to go into detail in
the second part of this class
about some of the specific
activities we do in 033,
but I'll give you some
examples from this list just
for concreteness.
So one of them, which I really
like to do in lecture actually,
is--
they all have funny names--
OK, so fingers on chest.
So this is having students vote
on a multiple choice question,
but using like fingers
on their chest.
So option one, option
two, option three.
And that way, the
students can't see what
other people are voting really.
They're not quite like,
oh, everybody else
is voting for one.
They can't really see, so
they tend to be more truthful.
A lot of times in
lecture, I ask them just
do they feel good
about something
or bad about something.
Another one, a fairly common
one-- think, pair, share.
So posing a question
to the class,
asking students
to think about it,
then to share their
ideas with a partner.
And then maybe go and
address the larger class.
And then a third one,
which I like just
because it has a nice name--
the name for it
is human Tableau.
And so this is
having groups create
living scenes which
relate to the classroom
concepts or discussion.
So that one's a little
bit more out there.
But these are the
types of activities
we're thinking about.
And of course, we went
through this list.
We looked at a whole
bunch of activities.
We're not going to end up
using all of them in 033.
But going through those list,
it was a really good exercise
for all of us.
It gave everyone a
much better sense
of what is active learning or
what can active learning be.
But even kind of
armed with that list,
it's still a lot to
tell your instructors,
here's your 278 activities,
now go, now do active learning.
So in addition to
this, I pre-planned
a lot of active
learning techniques
into each recitation.
So normally, before
active learning,
the way that I would
plan recitations
was strictly just for
technical content.
I would give my
instructors a handful
of major technical issues
they needed to hit on.
It helps keep our
recitations somewhat uniform
so that we can be fair on exams.
We do test the
technical material
on exams in this class.
Beyond that though,
my instructors
have a lot of leeway to
teach these topics however
they want, a lot of leeway
on how they teach in general.
I had never before
tried to steer them
in a particular direction.
But now, in addition to
that technical content,
what I would do is I would put
two or three active learning
activities or techniques
into each recitation.
So things like
pointing out places
where they could have
students break into groups
and think about a particular
question, pointing out
places where they could
hold a debate in the class.
And again, I'm going to talk
about these specific activities
we do in the second
part of this talk.
But planning
activities in this way
meant that my
instructors has had
a lot of ideas of
how they can make
this work in their sections.
Giving them multiple ideas and
multiple types of ideas really
meant that they could
pick the ones that they
were the most comfortable with.
So instead of saying, hey,
here's this really, really
out there idea, everybody
go try it, some of them
might try some of the
more extreme ones,
but everybody could
kind of find something
that they were comfortable with.
So get everybody on
board, plan things,
And the next thing that I
did was support my staff
as individuals.
So I didn't plan
these activities
and set the staff free.
I actually observed them
throughout the semester.
And I made sure
to stress that it
wasn't any sort of evaluation.
I was not there to
say, oh, boy, Karen,
this is really not working out.
I was just there to
see what was working
and what wasn't, so
that we could all
iterate on these things.
In practice, this was great.
I, of course, found
way more good things
in doing this than
anything problematic.
Most of my feedback
to my instructors
was, hey, you did this
really awesome thing,
you should do more
of that, and can we
share it with everybody else.
And so, I really,
in the end kind
of thought of myself more
as a cheerleader for them
and what they were doing,
than someone who was coming in
are really critiquing anything.
I also got a lot of
great ideas from them,
both in how to present certain
technical content and twists
on some of the active
learning techniques
that I had suggested.
So related to that, I'm
observing them as individuals,
but we would also
talk a lot as a group
about how this was going.
Every staff meeting
we'd take time
to talk about what went
well the previous week.
Our instructors would
share active learning ideas
that they tried, report
on how they went.
This was really nice.
It got some of my more
hesitant instructors kind
of on board with this,
to say like, oh, well,
that person tried it and it
seemed like it went really
well.
Maybe I'll try that next time.
And of course, the
thing that turned out
to be so great about this,
is that all of my instructors
have these amazing ideas on
how to teach certain things.
But to them, it
doesn't seem special,
like this is just always the way
I've taught operating systems.
And so, now we have this
space where we're getting
to share all of these ideas.
A lot of them relate to how
our active learning has gone.
But sometimes it's just,
hey, I taught this paper
this really cool way.
It has also-- the fact that
we've now kind of fostered
this space for discussion
at every staff meeting,
everybody is pretty
willing to bring up
things that aren't going as
well, to maybe come in and say,
hey, I tried this
active learning thing
and it did not work at all.
What do you all think?
Is there something I could
have done differently?
Is this just not something
that will work for our class?
And so that has been
really, really great,
having this space for my staff
to kind of reflect on this
and not feel judged in any way.
So this is the first part of
getting active learning to work
in 033, which was a
lot of staff training.
But now the second part--
what do we actually do?
What are these activities?
I would like to give you some
specific examples from 033,
but I will also try to give you
some general feedback as well.
I realize you probably won't be
able to take the 033 activities
exactly into your classes,
so let me talk about some
of the common things that we do.
So these are things that
we've seen work really well
in our classes.
So one of the most common types
of active learning that we do
is one I have already
referenced a lot, which
is to put students in small
groups, have them do something,
and then bring them back
for a class-wide discussion.
So let me give you some
really specific examples.
We have a recitation where we
talk about content distribution
networks.
The paper they read
describes various goals
of those networks, so
performance, reliability,
scalability, things like this.
And what we'll do
in that recitation
is we'll divide the
class up into groups.
And we'll have each
group think about what
aspects of the system
support a particular goal.
So you think about performance,
you think about reliability,
you think about
scalability, et cetera.
And then we'll bring the
class back to a discussion
once they've thought
about that for a while.
Another example, when we talk
about naming in the Unix file
system, we start by asking
them, what things have names?
What things in Unix have names?
And again, we'll
put them in groups.
We'll try to get every group to
come up with as many things as
possible.
Because when we bring
them back together,
we'll try to get a different
thing from every group.
So you can't all
just say files, you
have to say like files, and
directories, and processes.
And there's a lot of things
in Unix that have names.
I'm not here to make
you Unix experts.
And so, in both of those
examples, like I said,
we'll bring the class back
together for a discussion.
We'll try to have each
group say something.
And as I said before, we've
seen very clearly, talking
in these small
groups before hand,
really makes the shyer
students a lot more confident.
And asking each group to
contribute to the discussion
means that we don't end up with
something that is dominated
by one or two groups.
Often, we'll even be a little
bit more relaxed about it.
We will just ask a big question,
some sort of thought question,
not just a tell me this
fact from the paper.
We'll break them up
in the small groups,
have them think about it,
and come back together
for a discussion.
It's nice, it breaks
up the recitation.
It gets them kind of
talking and doing things.
We occasionally will have
our TAs teach in this class.
And we encourage them to use
these techniques as well.
And one of them asked me
a really good question
that I realized I had
never thought about.
She said, what do I do
when they're in groups?
Like, do I just stand
there and stare at them?
Probably not, that's
probably not good.
So to tell you what we do
while they're in groups,
sometimes our instructors
might actually check in
with each group,
to say, oh, hey,
what are you guys
thinking about?
Sometimes, you're kind
of lightly monitoring,
you're walking around.
I know when I cover
recitations, sometimes
I use it as time to prep for
the thing that is coming next.
So if I need to draw
something on the board that's
going to take a minute,
I'll put you all in groups
so you can discuss
while I draw that.
So this works really
well as a technique
to get students
engaged and talking,
and honestly, it's also nice
from a classroom management
perspective.
It breaks things up, it gives
you a little break from talking
and you can drink some water.
So that is kind of
our starting point.
This is one thing where I
would say we do something
like this in almost every
single recitation, every Tuesday
and Thursday.
The second one is one
that I really like,
which is to have
the students debate.
It's a little bit harder
to work into a recitation.
You need a question
that can be debated.
For us, we have one
recitation where the students
read two short papers.
And the papers actually come
to opposing conclusions.
And so it's an interesting
lesson for them,
well, how could this
happen in science?
How could data say
two different things?
It is mind-blowing for them,
honestly, it's pretty wild.
And so we'll split
them into two teams.
And we'll give them each
a paper, have them debate.
The students usually
really like this.
They love to argue, so they're
very excited to do this.
It does involve a
bit more monitoring.
You want to make sure that
one team, or one person,
or one team doesn't dominate.
To combat that, we'll always
have the teams converse
beforehand, kind of get
your argument together
so you're ready to
prepare it for the class.
I personally think something
like that could also
work in small groups.
Maybe you have groups of
four, teams of two, debating.
I will say, when I've taught
this recitation, of these two
papers, there's like a
clear winner in my mind.
The last time I taught
this, the opposing team
made some very salient points.
So they really do
well with this.
So this one is one that
I think is really fun,
just a little bit more
difficult to work in
because of what it requires.
A third one, something
that we've actually
started doing more of this year,
is having them draw pictures.
So we'll ask them, in
groups, to draw pictures
on the board of whatever
system we're talking about,
or maybe some component
of that system.
And what we end up
with is a wide variety
of drawings of varying
levels of artistic skill.
And we can come
together and talk about,
what is each drawing showing?
What are the common
things that we're seeing
in all of these depictions?
What level of abstraction
is each drawing capturing?
That's something that comes
up a lot for us in 033.
I like this for a few reasons.
For 033 specifically, part of
our communication curriculum
involves teaching the students
how to design and draw figures.
So this, for us, this is just a
great way for them to practice.
It also forces them to figure
out exactly what the system is
doing.
And so we can expose
some areas where
they might have
missed something,
which always happens.
We expect them to read the
papers before they come in.
They should be able
to draw something.
It might not be perfect, and
that gives us a great space
to explore that, like
why was this confusing?
What is it about the paper
that made this confusing?
It's also just fun.
So the students get
a kick out of it.
Now the last activity that I
want to talk about, this is,
I'm going to say
that this is one
of our more extreme activities.
We actually do it
pretty frequently.
We will have students
act things out.
Also, the hardest
to make an icon for,
I just didn't know
what to do there.
They're acting, you can tell.
Now, I tell people about this
a lot, and whenever I say it,
like, oh, we act things
out in 033 all the time,
they are for sure intrigued.
They are not sure exactly
what that would entail.
So I was going to have
you all do this activity,
but we're half going
to do this activity.
So I kind of want to go
through one of our examples
actually in detail.
We have them act out a
system called MapReduce.
But for this to
make any sense, you
need to understand a little
bit about what MapReduce does.
So you're going to become--
I don't want to say
MapReduce experts,
MapReduce novices for
the next five minutes.
All right, so, brief aside
of technical material.
MapReduce is this
system for performing
parallel computation.
And so here's the
canonical example.
We have a large piece of text.
The Library of Congress
has a lot of books in it.
These books, we're
going to digitize this,
and so the data from
these books is spread out
on all different machines.
So we have a lot of computers.
Let's say, you all
can be computers.
So each one of you has a book
from the Library of Congress.
And here's the problem
that we want to solve,
the canonical MapReduce problem.
We want to count the
number of occurrences
of each word in
this entire corpus.
So I want to know, how
many times does the word
apple appear?
How many times does
the word ball appear?
the word the appear?
OK?
It's the canonical problem.
You all don't look like you
actually want to know that.
You do, you want to know
how many times the word
apple occurs in the
Library of Congress.
So you can imagine doing
that with one computer, where
that computer just reads
every book in sequence
and keeps track of these counts.
And that would be very slow.
So instead, what we
can do is we can have
multiple computers participate.
You all have a portion of
the Library of Congress.
You all can read your data.
You can make accounts
for your pieces of data.
This is the map phase.
And then we need some way to
kind of combine those results.
So if Dipa finds that the
word apple occurred five times
in her text, if Jesse found
that it occurred six times,
I need some way to add those up.
That would be the reduce phase.
And so part of the
insight of this system
is that there are a lot of
common problems in computer
science that can be
described this way.
This is a system that
came from Google.
So Google is doing this
on your data all the time.
They are mapping and reducing
everything about you.
So let's see how that
would actually work,
how this system would work.
Jessie, come play your
role in this thing.
JESSIE: Do I have
to wear the hat?
PROFESSOR: You do have to wear
the hat, it's active learning.
I've got to write master on it.
JESSIE: I'm ready.
PROFESSOR: I think a
lot of things in life
should be more fun.
So there's really no reason
for Jessie to wear this hat.
But there's also not a reason
for her not to wear this hat.
So--
JESSIE: There might be a reason.
AUDIENCE: This is about
who this is fun for.
JESSIE: Fortunately, I can't see
you, so now I feel comfortable.
PROFESSOR: Well, you can tilt
the hat back a little bit
maybe.
So in MapReduce, there
is the one machine
that acts as the coordination
for this, the master machine,
as Jessie is so--
doing such a great
job acting for us.
And so what the
master's job would be--
you don't have-- you're just--
we just want to visualize you.
You're just a prop, yes.
So it would start by
assigning jobs to workers.
Now you all, I didn't make hats
for all of you, there wasn't--
I know, I'm very sorry,
but you're all workers.
Only the master gets a hat.
All right, so you
are all workers.
So one of the first things
Master Jessie would do,
would be to assign
map jobs to workers.
And she would tell you
things like exactly what data
to operate on.
So imagine a scenario where
you, a worker machine,
has data from a ton of
different corpuses on it.
So Jessie actually
has to say, OK,
worry about the Library of
Congress part of your data.
And you would begin
operating on that.
You'd count your words.
And you'd write out some
results to your disk,
that you also have
as a machine in this.
And then when you were done,
you would report back to Jessie.
And you'd tell her some various
meta information, kind of like,
these are the
words that I found.
You don't have to send
her all of your results,
because the Library of Congress
is big, you have a lot of data.
But you might tell Jessie,
hey, I found apple.
Now, once all of you are
finished doing your map jobs,
Jessie has all of this
kind of meta information,
she can start assigning
the reduce jobs.
And the reduce jobs are
a little bit different.
So Dipa if it was your job to
reduce, say, the word apple,
you need to know
a couple things.
You need to know, well,
which one of these machines
actually found the word apple.
It's not necessarily
they're going
to be in every piece of data.
And Jessie would be
able to tell you that.
She'd basically say, hey,
Dipa contact these workers,
they have the data you need,
you can add them together,
in this example.
MapReduce functions can be
much more complex than this.
I thought let's start slow.
All right, so the reduce
workers would go, you'd reduce,
you'd report results
back to Jessie,
and then we'd have
our full counts.
I'm trying to decide how long
I want you to stand here,
and the answer is for
the rest of the talk,
but you can almost sit down.
All right, so this
is the basic--
JESSIE: I thought I'd
have more work to do.
PROFESSOR: I thought
that would be a lot.
I didn't prep you for that.
Don't go yet, though.
JESSIE: I'm just moving over.
PROFESSOR: So this is the
basic idea of MapReduce.
This is the type of thing
we'd actually expect
the students to know coming in.
They've read the paper, and
they should understand this sort
of level of coordination.
But there are a lot of
details that we left out.
For instance, I didn't
ask you all, hey, what
happens if a machine fails?
Worker Dipa crashes,
what do we do?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: All the time, right?
Is that data that she
was storing, is it
anywhere else in the system?
How do we know?
What if she had half
finished the job?
What do we do?
Or even, what if there was
no crash, but like let's say
the worker Janet is just running
really slow, like she's going,
she's working hard, but
everyone else is finished
and we're just waiting on Janet.
And these are those
types of things.
Those are the interesting
things about MapReduce.
That's the point where there
are tradeoffs for the students
to think about.
So it's not just
important to think about,
oh gosh, what does happen if
a machine crashes or is slow,
but why does it happen that way.
So to do this, we actually
have them act out this system.
And from the way that
I've described it here,
you might think, well, I have
one student be the master
and everybody else
is a worker, that's
kind of what I was
setting you all up for.
This is not actually
how we do it.
Normally-- for one, it
doesn't work with the size
of our recitations.
Even here, this is a lot
of workers for one student
to be in charge of.
And also, if Jessie was
maybe more of a shy student,
she's like this is the
worst day of my entire life.
Katrina has made me wear a
hat, and I have to stand--
I am in charge of
everything, it's not good.
It's not good.
So in practice, here's
how we do this activity.
You can sit down if you want.
You don't have to
be here anymore.
JESSIE: Should I
keep the hat on?
PROFESSOR: I think,
definitely, yes.
I think absolutely.
So we do start by
assigning students roles.
But we will usually
have them in teams.
So there will be a master team.
Each worker will be a team of
maybe two or three students.
This is good for
a lot of reasons.
Again, for the reason of
getting the shyer students
to be a little bit
more comfortable,
no one student is in
charge of something.
From a logistical
standpoint, again, I
glazed over many a
detail in MapReduce,
but you can imagine that
the master has a lot to do,
a lot to keep track of.
And so we will often,
we'll have our master team.
And we'll actually give each
student in that team a task.
So one might run the
clock, timing in the system
is important.
We'll see an example
of that in a second.
One keeps track of what
map tasks to complete.
One assigns the tasks,
things like that.
We have found-- we've
actually done this activity
a number of times.
It gets better every time.
One of the things we
learned the most quickly
is that the master--
we had to give
the students who were
doing the master extremely
detailed instructions.
If we just said do
the master's job,
they were not ready for that.
In some sections, in fact,
some of my instructors
prefer to do this where the
instructor just is the master,
and so they can be kind of
in charge of coordination.
Workers in this example get a
little bit of an easier job.
Again, we're putting them
in teams of two to three.
Sometimes we might give them
a sheet with words on it,
and actually ask them
to count the words.
Sometimes we'll give them
a sheet that kind of just
says here's the words in your
data and here are the counts.
That might seem like, oh,
gosh what's the point,
they're not actually
doing the worker job.
Counting the words in the text
is not the interesting part
of this system.
So sometimes we'll
just skip that.
It also, again, lets us do
some very precise things
with timing.
So once these
roles are assigned,
we're going to run the protocol.
So the person keeping
track of the master clock
will advance it, one click,
two clicks, et cetera.
Various map jobs will complete.
Most of the time, when we
give them a paper that says,
here's your words and your
counts, we'll also say,
hey, it takes three clock
cycles for you to complete.
And so once the clock
has ticked three times,
they'll report back
to the master team.
Because of how we set up
those map tasks, some of them
will also fail.
Some of them will have
papers that say, oh, I
failed after click two.
And they have to
announce it to the class.
And at that point, we pause.
What happens?
What happens when
a machine fails?
What does MapReduce do?
Why does it do that?
The spoiler for you all
in MapReduce, the master
will reassign that
task to somewhere else.
And part of that
challenge is making sure
that the new worker has
access to the data that
was on the crashed machine.
MapReduce replicates data, so
we talk about how that happens.
And the protocol continues.
The students will find that one
map task, it hasn't crashed,
but it's taking
a very long time.
And that's another good
point for discussion.
What does MapReduce do?
Does it just wait?
In practice, it restarts
the task in another machine.
And then, so, oh, there's a
question, these two machines
are running the same thing.
What do we do?
Who do we listen to?
How do we get the data?
And this is why the timing of
that activity is so important,
because a lot of the discussion
points about MapReduce
come from what we do when things
are slow or when things fail.
So being in control of
that timing is crucial.
We do have some variations
on this activity though.
One of our instructors this year
had students count characters
instead of words, same idea.
But of the workers was
counting Russian characters
instead of English.
So they just organically were
much slower than the rest
of the class.
And that was kind of a
nice way to show that.
Many of our instructors
have the students
count types of candy
instead of words.
And we bring them candy.
That's a big hit.
In fact, after we did
this recitation this year,
one of our students asked
why can't every recitation
be like the MapReduce one.
It is not clear
how much the candy
factored into that question.
So it has taken us
quite a few iterations
to get that activity working.
And again, I know
you're not all teaching
MapReduce in your courses.
You're not going to take
that activity to you.
But the things that
were interesting for us,
having the students in teams
for each of these roles
made a huge difference,
both in terms
of making sure they were all
doing the correct things,
but just getting them
more comfortable with it.
I will tell you, the
students go for this.
They are into it.
They map and reduce.
They do not think it's stupid,
which is very, very nice.
And making sure that the master
has these exceedingly detailed
instructions, figuring out
how to make the timing work,
so that all of the things
we wanted to discuss
would actually happen.
And so really the activity
is the way I describe it--
Karen, this is
how Karen does it.
Karen, you're the authoritative
source on how we do MapReduce--
yeah.
I want to talk briefly about
another system we act out
because it's fun.
It's one of my favorite
things that we do.
It's much shorter.
We do this for a
system called Raft.
And Raft, like MapReduce is
this large distributed system
on a lot of machines.
Timing is also
important in Raft.
In particular, machines
set randomized timers.
I picked some random number
of seconds, milliseconds,
whatever.
And when that timer
expires, they do something.
So being able to act that out
is actually really crucial.
And we thought, gosh, how are
we going to randomize them?
And so one of my
instructors came up
with the best idea, which is to
have the students spin around
in a circle.
So like literally,
they're standing here,
and then they kind of-- they
do this, and it takes a while.
Because he figured
out that students
just walk around naturally
at different paces.
So they've effectively
randomized themselves.
Someone will finish first.
So I need you to imagine feel
like you're walking around MIT,
and you're just
kind of like, oh,
what's going on in this class.
And you see seven
or eight students up
at the front of the room just
very quietly spinning around
in place, while all of the
other students are like--
the person who
finishes first wins.
And so who-- who is it?
Who's going to be the next
leader of this election
cycle in Raft.
It's really-- it
looks ridiculous,
but it works so well.
And it brings me a lot of joy.
So to kind of wrap
up our activities
before I get to results,
effectively, how
has this worked for us--
again, we do all of
these things a lot.
This one in particular,
small groups,
a class wide discussion--
although acting things out, we
act a lot of things out now.
We've gotten pretty
good at that.
And the key component for
us has been recognizing
in all of these
cases, the students
are more comfortable if they're
not doing something alone,
if they have at least one other
person on their team doing
whatever it is they need
to do in that recitation.
And since we do something
like this in every recitation,
the students just
come to expect it.
I mean, they go for it.
Sometimes, I'll come in
and cover a recitation.
And despite
observations, I'm never
exactly sure how my
instructors are leaving things.
And so, I always
start by asking,
like, hey, I'm going to
put you all in groups,
is that something
you're used to.
Every time, they're
like, yeah, we
do that every day, like of
course we can get into groups.
So again, even acting things
out, they really go for it.
We try to vary the
types of activities
that we do each week, to
keep everyone engaged,
to keep things interesting.
It's hard to act
ever system out.
And there's occasions where
an activity doesn't work.
The first time we tried
MapReduce, it was chaos.
But we thought it
was a cool thing.
So we just iterated.
We just tried it again
the next semester.
And in planning
all of these, we're
still very careful to make sure
that our activities actually
teach them things.
Like I said, all
of the recitations
have technical points
that they have to hit on.
A MapReduce activity
where they just
act out the system in its normal
use case, it would be fun,
but they're supposed to
come in knowing that.
So we really want to
design these activities
so that we're hitting on the
points we need to hit on.
So there is a lot of
planning that goes into this.
So now, for the final
part, did it work?
What got better?
I'll start with a few
actually quantitative things.
Sometimes when I tell
people about this endeavor,
they want to know,
are grades better?
Have the students'
grades improved?
How are they doing on exams?
I don't personally think that
that's the right question.
There is one aspect of
grading that has improved--
participation grades.
We assign a pretty large
portion of the final grade
to participation in recitation.
Again, we're asking
a lot of them.
We're expecting them to
demonstrate certain skills
in recitation, so they
are graded accordingly.
And we're seeing students earn
higher participation grades
now.
I'm comfortable
interpreting that as they
are participating more.
We are also giving them
a lot more opportunities
to participate.
Related to that,
one of the things
that we've gained
from this experience
is just a better
understanding of what it means
to participate in our class.
For a long time
to us, it kind of
meant, well, does this
student answer questions
when I ask them a question.
But now it means, are they
coming prepared to class?
Are they engaged in group work?
Are they listening
to other students
and to their instructor?
Are they participating in
class wide discussions?
There is more opportunities
for students to participate.
We are much clearer about
how we assign this grade.
So not only have
the grades improved,
but the students are noticeably
more relaxed about this grade.
I get fewer complaints
about this grade,
which is great for me.
And they know that if they
come prepared and ready to do
the work, they'll be fine.
AUDIENCE: The grade
for the recitation
is separate from
the course grade?
PROFESSOR: It's part of the
final grade in the course.
A percentage of the final
grade is from participation
in recitation.
So we also surveyed the
students during the semester.
And we were largely
asking questions about
do you feel comfortable
in the recitations.
Largely, yes, they did.
In our final survey,
overwhelmingly the students
felt that these activities
improved their engagement.
So these things are all good.
I don't think they
really captured
though what has been so
great about this endeavor
for our class.
And so in preparing
this talk, I spoke
to a couple of
instructors who have been
with me for a number of years.
So they've seen the class
through its non-active learning
era, through the dark times,
as well as the current era.
And so I stole a few quotes
from them to kind of sum
up what I think is made
this approach better
for the students.
So let's turn to number one.
The first is that I think the
students actually understand
the algorithms better.
In particular, if we're
acting something out,
it gives them a visceral
experience of the finer points
and edge conditions.
It's really easy to
slide over things
if one reads a paper
quickly, and we're
asking them to read a lot.
Second instructor, I think
that it's much better when
there are pairs
discussing a solution
or when we're doing a game.
People are more likely to notice
a flaw in something I've said
or in someone else's answer.
And they ask better questions.
Plus, I think it's
reassuring either
to find out that a classmate
is just as confused
or to find out that a classmate
knows a ton about the subject.
And then the last
one, which I think
really sums up how things
have been for our students,
is this one.
I think the students are more
engaged because they are asked
to be more active participants.
There's a greater sense of
camaraderie between them
because of their interactions.
So we're seeing these
students understanding
the details of the systems
better, while developing
this sense of camaraderie.
And honestly, that
has been huge for us.
Largely, I would say,
from my perspective
as the person in
charge, students
are buying into this class
more than they used to.
I get fewer complaints
across the board.
We're seeing them
work better together
in their team projects.
We're seeing them
be more engaged
in lecture and in tutorial, even
though recitations was really
where this active
learning push happened.
And this whole thing
has been beneficial,
not just for the students,
but also for the staff.
There was a little
hesitance at first.
Active learning
can be a hard sell.
It involves more
work for everyone.
It takes a lot of planning.
It can be a nerve-wracking
way to teach if you've never
taught it before.
Imagine coming into
a room of students
you don't know very well,
and say, OK, five of your
are going to be on
the master team,
let's go, I made
you all hats, right?
But now, one of my
instructors said,
there's a modest
amount of competition
among the recitation instructors
to work out schemes and games.
So it feels like there's both
a reward for applying myself,
but there's also less
need for perfection.
It's helped that
we're encouraging
active learning is an
approach, because it makes
it feel like less
of a risk for me
to try some new unconventional
approach that occurs to me.
So I'll tell you one of
the highlights for me,
as a person sort of
overseeing this operation.
So this happened at the
end of last semester.
Again, that's the
first time we're really
putting this scheme into place.
And near the end,
my instructors--
I got this email
from the instructors
about one of the
final recitations.
And the recitation
was about a system
called DNS SEC, secure DNS.
So it deals with security.
DNS prevents certain types of
attacks on a system called DNS.
That's all you need
to know DNS SEC.
So the first instructor
described an activity
they had done, where they
had groups draw diagrams
of their attacks on
the board in parallel
and then talked
through each diagram,
with the students explaining
the problems and the approaches.
And the instructor
noted that they engaged,
they laughed, they collaborated,
they learned more about
how design figures to tell
the story they wanted to tell.
And I got this email,
and I was so excited.
Because this was not an activity
that I had planned for them.
This is just something
they had done.
And I thought, it's happened,
finally it's happened.
And then I get a second email.
And so a second
instructor responded
saying that that sounded great.
And what they had done,
they'd had a group of students
work out how DNS would work
for a particular scenario, so
the original system.
And then two additional groups
joined that first group,
worked through how
different attacks would
affect that scenario.
And then a fourth
group acted as DNS SEC,
and explain how DNS SEC
would prevent such attacks.
So to brand new ideas,
both really good,
both really different.
And this is so exciting.
And then we get to
instructor number three.
And I've never been
able to figure out
a way to summarize this email.
So I have to quote
it for you directly.
"In my recitation, we
had a marriage proposal
that went bad when a romantic
rival launched an attack
to destroy the relationship.
A second group used
a different attack
to induce peasants to send
their taxes to a scammer.
All of these attacks
were then prevented
by the use of DNS SEC.
After each play, we did a replay
with deep structure analysis
that made the analogy between
the play and DNS explicit.
Overall, a pretty
fun recitation and I
was impressed with the
creativity, enthusiasm,
and acting talent the
students displayed."
So this was amazing.
This was like such--
this email thread
is just such a triumph for me.
I have it highlighted
and saved in my email.
And this has continued
on since last semester.
I get like one of these
email threads a week
now, with my instructor telling
me all of the cool things
that they have done.
So the last thing, which I hope
has come through in this talk,
it was a lot of work to
get this to happen in 033.
I cannot in good faith stand
here tell you active learning
is a breeze, you can just add
it in, five minutes of prep time
before the class.
It's a lot of work.
But this class is
so much fun now.
It's fun for me to run.
It's fun for
instructors to teach.
I don't know how many
people would tell you
that their 400-person
class is fun to run.
But I have a great time.
And the amount of enjoyment that
we get out of teaching 033 this
way really comes through
for the students.
And I think that's another
component of what has helped
them engage more in this class.
So it has worked
really well for us.
I hope that you get some
practical things that you can
try out in your own classes.
And I'm happy to take questions
or to delegate questions off
to Jesse and Karen.